<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The death of the tvvo renowned kings of Sweden and Bohemia, happening both in one and the same year and moneth; viz: in November 1632 Publikely lamented in a sermon, held before a princely, noble, and frequent assembly, in the high-Dutch congregation at the Hague by Mr. Frederike Schloer, minister of Gods word. Translated out of the High-Dutch printed coppie.</title>
            <author>Schloer, Frederike.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 59KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B15663</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837749</idno>
  <idno type="VID">177534</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240880668</idno>
  <idno type="STC">STC 21819</idno>
  <idno type="STC">ESTC S101946</idno>
  
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99837749e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B15663)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 177534)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1034:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The death of the tvvo renowned kings of Sweden and Bohemia, happening both in one and the same year and moneth; viz: in November 1632 Publikely lamented in a sermon, held before a princely, noble, and frequent assembly, in the high-Dutch congregation at the Hague by Mr. Frederike Schloer, minister of Gods word. Translated out of the High-Dutch printed coppie.</title>
                  <author>Schloer, Frederike.</author>
                  <author>T. H., fl. 1633.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 48 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I. D[awson] for Nicholas Bourne and are to be sold at his shop, at the south entrance of the Royall Exchange,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1633.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Translated by T.H.--STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: A lamentation sermon.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-01 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:177534:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177534:1"/>
            <p>THE DEATH OF THE TVVO RENOWNED KINGS OF <hi>SWEDEN</hi> AND <hi>BOHEMIA▪</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Happening both in one and the same yeare and moneth; <hi>viz:</hi> in NOVEMBER 1632.</p>
            <p>Publikely lamented in a Sermon, held be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a Princely, Noble, and frequent Assem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly, in the <hi>High-Dutch</hi> Congregation <hi>at the</hi> HAGVE</p>
            <p>By M<seg rend="sup">r</seg>. FREDERIKE SCHLOER, Minister <hi>of Gods Word.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Translated out of the <hi>High-Dutch</hi> Printed COPPIE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>I. D.</hi> for <hi>Nicolas Bourne</hi> and are to be sold at his Shop, at the South entrance of the <hi>Royall Exchange.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1633.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:177534:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:177534:2"/>
            <head>The Entrance.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloved, in our Lord and Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our Iesus Christ;</hi> It hath pleased almighty God to visite whole <hi>Christendome,</hi> and especially our own deare <hi>Country</hi> and <hi>Nation,</hi> but most neerely the greatest part of this Assembly, with a very heavie, but well-deserved afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and calamitie, in pulling downe by a never-lesse expected death, two of the chiefest Pillars
<pb facs="tcp:177534:3"/> of his <hi>Church,</hi> two of the chiefest Patrones of true <hi>Religion,</hi> two of the chiefest Instruments of his <hi>Glorie;</hi> the two Royall Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties of <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Bohemia,</hi> in that moment of Time, when our hopes were at the best, that GOD by them would have saved His <hi>Israel.</hi> Wel, <hi>Beloved,</hi> Our unmea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>surable sinnes have most justly deserved this, and much more, and worse: yea, GODS mercie and goodnesse it is, that wee are not utterly consumed; And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause we cannot otherwise con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude and pronounce from this our grievous losse and punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but that the wrath of the <hi>Almightie</hi> is kindled against the continuance of our sinfull cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses,
<pb facs="tcp:177534:3"/> it is most requisite, that with unfained repentance, and effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all resolutions of serving GOD more carefully then ever yet wee have done, we goe to meete the LORD, and to hold his hands from destroying us utterly. To this purpose now wee are met in the Vallie of (<hi>Bochim,</hi>) not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to lift up our mournfull voi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in lamenting and bewailing our incomparable losses, in the death of those two pious and He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roike <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Champions;</hi> but to confesse our murthering sins unto the LORD, to repent and reforme our selues, to pray to GOD for a gracious pardon: and that thus reconciled, He would bee pleased with the dew of his
<pb facs="tcp:177534:4"/> blessed comforts to refresh, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, and cherish the Royall &amp; Princely <hi>Houses,</hi> and all the true hearted Friends &amp; Dependants of those deceased <hi>Worthies;</hi> that He would not reject, but in mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie regard us; And besides to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue instruction out of His sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Word▪ how we are to frame our lives and courses in time to come, that the <hi>Almightie</hi> may heare our prayers, &amp; let his gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cious face to shine againe upon our troubled soules. But because of our selues wee are altogether unable, to thinke one good thought, much lesse to speake or performe any good thing, let us joyn in humble petition to God the Father of our Lord <hi>Iesus
<pb facs="tcp:177534:4"/> Christ,</hi> for the assistance of his <hi>blessed Spirit,</hi> that our hearts may be cleansed and sanctified, and his holy Word preached may bring fruit in us, to his glorie, and the eternall welfare and salvation of our poore soules. Almighty, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall and &amp;c.</p>
            <closer>Our Father, &amp;c.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:177534:5"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:177534:5"/>
            <head>A Lamentation Sermon. TEXTVS.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>2. SAM. 1. ver. 19. 20.</bibl>
               <q>And <hi>David</hi> lamented: The beautie of <hi>Israel</hi> is slaine upon thy high places; How are the Mightie fallen? Tell it not in <hi>Gath,</hi> publish it not in the streetes of <hi>Askalon,</hi> least the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the <hi>Philistins</hi> reioyce, least the Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of the uncircumcised triumph.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>VGVSTVS <hi>mortuus est, The King is dead:</hi> For thus were the <hi>Romans</hi> wont to begin their <hi>Epicaedies</hi> after the death of their Mighties. And why should not wee now begin likewise in the same manner, that as we may reade one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers heart and disposition in his face, so you may know the drift of this our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:177534:6"/>
               <hi>Lamenting Sermon</hi> in the very entrance; <hi>The Kings are dead.</hi> We read 2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. 1. 2. that, after that great victorie which God gaue unto <hi>David</hi> against <hi>Absolom,</hi> the day of tryumph was turned into a day of mourning unto all the people, onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause they heard some whisperings of the Courtiers that <hi>the King wept.</hi> How much greater cause have wee, <hi>Beloved,</hi> in the midst of our victories to keepe a day of mourning? The Courtiers not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly telling us <hi>The Queenes weepe,</hi> but with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, <hi>The Kings are dead.</hi> That is able to melt a stone, but this the wicked'st heart, which is more flintie then any rocke. <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved,</hi> me thinkes, it were enough and sufficient to turn your hearts into springs and your eyes into rivers of teares, if we should rehearse no other word unto you this houre, but <hi>The Kings are dead;</hi> not onely <hi>Kings,</hi> but <hi>those Kings,</hi> that concerne us so neerly, in whom we were so much interessed; <hi>Those Kings</hi> who had so straight a relation to the whole <hi>Christian Church; Those Kings</hi> that so much suffered, so much performed to the righting of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:177534:6"/> Gods honour, to deliver his Church from the Enemies of the Gospell, to spread Religion, to relieve and release the oppressed, and to subvert the Throne of <hi>Antichrist. Those Kings are dead,</hi> The Crownes are fallen off from our heads; Woe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us! for we have sinned <hi>Tiberius</hi> geares and mockes the <hi>Ilienses,</hi> when they came somewhat late unto him to condole the death of <hi>Augustus,</hi> answering them, <hi>Et ego doleo Hectorem vestrum esse mortuum;</hi> And I am sorrie you lost your Captaine <hi>Hector,</hi> who was dead many hundred yeares before. So some wretched scoffers may conceive we lament the death of <hi>those Kings</hi> very late; Alas! <hi>Beloved,</hi> we lament them too too soone, according to the mindes and wishes of all sincere hearted; of whom I dare say, there is none, but saith with me in his heart, <hi>Ah! deare Kings would to God I had dyed for you, deare Kings, deare Princes. David</hi> could not speake a word when he was troubled, as he confes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seth of himselfe, <hi>Psal. 77. 4. Thou holdest mine eyes waking, I am so troubled, that I cannot speake.</hi> Thus, my <hi>Beloved,</hi> did <hi>novitas rei,</hi> the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:177534:7"/> strange, un expected, and altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looked-for newes of the death of these great Kings, so confound our thoughts, disturbe our memories, and locke up our tongues, that we could neither be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, nor feele, nor speake of our losse, till the third, fourth, and some follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dayes were past; and then we began from our <hi>Ecstasis,</hi> and confused rap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to come againe to our selues, and to see what, and where, and how we are now; namely, poore, scattering, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>saken sheepe. Vnbeliefe strucke <hi>Zachari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as</hi> dumbe; beliefe unloosened againe the tye of his tongue, and resolved it into a <hi>Magnificat.</hi> To our unbeliefe it seemed impossible, that <hi>Those Kings, Such Kings,</hi> could be taken away <hi>in limin victoriae,</hi> in the entrance to an accomplished victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie; <hi>in vestibulo felicitatis,</hi> in the very gate of our temporall happinesse. And hence was our lamenting deferred hitherto, that we have not yet mourned in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like to witnesse our humiliation, and the unfained sorrowes of our hearts. But <hi>now we beleeue, therefore we speake, but we are sore troubled.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:177534:7"/>
            <p>But <hi>Beloved,</hi> let us mourne so that we doe not fall neither into temptation, nor into despaire; Let not Gods providence be prejudiced by the extremitie and boundlesnesse of our complaints; Let not us by our excessiue and un-christian teares, grudge unto those Royall soules the rest and happinesse they haue obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, nor disable our selues to the worke in hand, the hearing of Gods blessed word: but let us mourne as <hi>Christians,</hi> and not as <hi>Heathens,</hi> who mourne without hope; For there is a great difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the mourning of <hi>Gentiles,</hi> and that of the <hi>Faithfull,</hi> as we see <hi>Gen.</hi> 50. 2. 9. The <hi>Egyptians</hi> mourning 70. dayes for <hi>Ia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cob▪</hi> but <hi>Ioseph</hi> 7. dayes onely, though for his Father. So let us shew our selues to be rather <hi>Iosephites,</hi> then <hi>Egyptians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Alas! say many, should we so soone for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get those Kings? Those Annointed of the Lord, who were the comfort of our hearts, by whom we hoped God should haue saved his <hi>Israel?</hi> No, my <hi>Beloved, Wee may as soone forget them, as our right hands, our longue will cleaue to the roofe of our mouthes if wee
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:177534:8"/> doe not remember them?</hi> But though we may and shall remember them for ever, yet we must not for euer mourne for them. Water is good to bathe, wash, &amp; cleanse, but not to drowne our selues in it. So Teares are good, in some sort to cleanse our selues by them from our sinnes, to refresh us in our heavinesse (for after we haue once given our eyes free scope of weeping, our hearts are eased and grow lighter) but not to plunge &amp; drown our selues in despairing and perpetual mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning; And therefore let us now once more powre out our hearts, emptie our mournfull eyes, and once more satisfie our Christian sympathie and affection with unfained and Christian repentance; that we may afterwards, as alwayes we should have done, set our hearts onely upon God, turne our eyes alone to him, and give all our affections wholly over unto the <hi>Almightie.</hi> To this end let us consider the words of our Text, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of this Place, the cause and occasion of our meeting, and your sorrowfull hearts themselues have made choice off, and
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:177534:8"/> constraine us to meditate at present. For this place is now the very <hi>Bochim,</hi> the Vallie of Teares, <hi>where the people lift up their voices and weepe.</hi> The occasion is <hi>Marah,</hi> bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternesse; for the <hi>Almightie</hi> hath greatly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted and humbled us. Your eyes and hearts are full of weeping &amp; lamenting; nothing therefore could more fitly be preached unto you, but <hi>Threni,</hi> Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions; where the Place, the Occasion, &amp; Audience minister nothing but mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, weeping, and lamenting. Now these <hi>Threni,</hi> or this Lamentation, is not made by any private person, but by a King and Prophet, who is fitter to la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment a King but a King? Whose lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations can be holier then a Prophets? <hi>The beautie of Israel is slaine upon thy high places, How are the mightie fallen?</hi> As long as wee weepe with <hi>David,</hi> we cannot doe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>misse; but we must as well end, as begin with him: and thus our lamenting will be acceptable to God, commendable a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men, and profitable to our selues, that as <hi>now wee sow in teares, so wee may reape with ioy and comfort.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:177534:9"/>
            <p>Three maine things offer themselues to our consideration;</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. A Lamentation, <hi>And David lamented.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. A description of the deceased and of their end; <hi>The beautie of Israel is slaine; How are the mightie fallen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. An Instruction and advertisement, <hi>Tell it not in Gath, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>In the first is our dutie, <hi>to lament;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the second the object, for what; that <hi>The beautie of Israel is fallen, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the third the measure; <hi>weepe, lament so,</hi> that thereby you make no sport and pastime to the wicked, and least by it they take occasion to insult over you.</p>
            <p>In the first we see our portraiture, and <hi>contra-fact,</hi> as we now doe, &amp; ought to appeare: <hi>Lamenting</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the second we have a picture drawn of the Deceased, their lively linea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: <hi>The beautie of Israel, the mightie Ones.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the third we have a full draught of the wicked, with the native colours of their present disposition: <hi>Insolent re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioycings</hi> and <hi>tryumphs.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:177534:9"/>
            <p>Let us ascend one step and degree af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the other, and first of all, see and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider our present estate and condition, cast downe, drooping and lamenting, from those words of the 17. verse, which have reference to our Text: <hi>And David lamented.</hi>
            </p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <head>OF THE FIRST.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>David,</hi> that Man according to <hi>Gods</hi> heart, lamenteth here for <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than.</hi> It might seeme, he had but little reason to lament for <hi>Saul,</hi> his Enemy, his Persecutor, and a wicked man; though reason enough for <hi>Ionathan,</hi> whose love he esteemed <hi>beyond the love of women:</hi> Not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding, he lamenteth <hi>Saul,</hi> as his Father in Law, his King, and the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed of the Lord, although he dyed in his sinnes. By how much more then have we cause to lament and mourne <hi>for those Annoynted of the Lord,</hi> who besides their outward annointment of the Priest, had received withall, and were sanctified by the inward of the <hi>holy
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:177534:10"/> Ghost.</hi> The <hi>Christian</hi> man, as it is his duty to mourne and lament, under any kind of crosse &amp; calamitie <hi>God</hi> sends upon him; so he is especially obliged herevnto upō the death of his Magistrate, of his King and Prince, whom <hi>God</hi> had set as <hi>Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerent</hi> over him. <hi>Eccles 3. 4. There is a time of weeping</hi> appointed by <hi>God;</hi> and as fish, flesh, and other creatures are not good nor wholesome to eate out of their sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son: so is joy and laughter unchristian, if it be unseasonable. <hi>Isaac</hi> mourned 3. yeare over his mother: <hi>Iacob</hi> 22. yeares for his sonne. The <hi>Rabbines</hi> tell us, that <hi>Adam</hi> mourned 100. yeares for his sonne <hi>Abel:</hi> The <hi>Egyptians</hi> raised a monument of their mourning for <hi>Iacob</hi> at <hi>Abel-Mitzraim:</hi> The <hi>Iewes</hi> did the like for <hi>Iosias</hi> in the vallie of <hi>Megiddo:</hi> Yea, the <hi>Iewes</hi> were wont to hire men for to lament their dead, who cut and pricked themselues, that they might weepe in good earnest.</p>
               <p>Lamentations and weepings are of three sorts, that are required of <hi>Christians,</hi> as the <hi>Schooles</hi> doe divide them out of <hi>Gods</hi> word. 1. <hi>Lacrymae doloris,</hi> griefe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teares:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:177534:10"/> 2. <hi>Lacrymae compassionis,</hi> fellow-fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling teares. 3. <hi>Lacrymae penitentiae,</hi> repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting teares; The first are personall; the second for others; the third for both.</p>
               <p n="1">1 <hi>Lacrymae doloris.</hi> Griefe-teares, are those which we shed every one in his private and particular crosse and afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when any evill befalls us, as we are never unfurnished of occasions, from the cradle to the grave. Low grounds are commonly moist and waterie: The earth lieth <hi>in Centro mundi,</hi> in a deepe bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome; no marvaile, that it is a <hi>Vallie of teares;</hi> Hence we have so often cause to <hi>wash our couch with teares, to eate the bread of teares, to drinke teares, to cover the Altar of the Lord with teares. Malach.</hi> 2. 13. what ever we doe, where ever we are, we have cause of mourning, weeping, and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Lacrymae compassionis.</hi> Fellow-feeling teares, when we see or know others suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, we have likewise cause to mourne, as fellow-members of the same bodie. S. <hi>Austine</hi> gives a fine reason why we should compassionate others in their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:177534:11"/> misery, by this similitude: For, saith he, in a throng of people, one may easily tread upon another mans foot, &amp; cause him to say, <hi>Cur me calcas,</hi> why doest thou tread me? The foot, or the toe was hurt, and not the tongue, and yet the tongue complaineth, <hi>Cur me calcas?</hi> By reason of that amiable sympathie and friendship that is betweene the membets; Thus likewise should it be among <hi>Christians,</hi> if one suffer, all should be grieved and la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for it. It would be an uncomely thing, if one should weare a golden shoe upon one foot, and a woodden upon the other so unseemly it is in the Church of Christ, if there is disparitie of the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, if they have not all one and the same, as they have one <hi>God,</hi> one Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, one faith. And therefore <hi>Christ,</hi> as <hi>Paul</hi> persecuted the Church tooke it as done to himselfe, saying, <hi>Saul, Saul, why per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secutest thou me? Act. 9. 4. Me inquit, non meos, Me,</hi> saith Christ, not <hi>Mine,</hi> as <hi>Austine</hi> spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Lacrymae paenitentiae.</hi> Repenting teares, in both cases: Why doth the hand of
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:177534:11"/>
                  <hi>God</hi> lie upon us or others, but because we have sinned, therefore <hi>God</hi> chastiseth us for our sinnes, and sometimes others for our sake. Many times we draw the rod of <hi>God</hi> upon us, for, <hi>Flagitium &amp; fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gellum ut acus &amp; filum,</hi> sinne and punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment follow one another, as the needle and the threed, one makes way for the other. <hi>Numb.</hi> 32. 23. And as God doth oftentimes punish us in our owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons▪ so doe others eft-soones feele the rod of <hi>God</hi> for our sakes, and they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the punishment, that we deserved: <hi>God</hi> deales herein with us, as with great mens children, who are refrained from evill by seeing punishment inflicted up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on others; or as the Physitions deale sometimes with their Patients, when they have a rheume in their eyes, to open a veine in their necke or armes: Thus <hi>God</hi> many times chastiseth us in our goods, friends, children, kindred, for our correction and instruction. Many <hi>Israelites</hi> were put to death by reason of <hi>Achan:</hi> more for <hi>Davids</hi> sinne. <hi>Abimelechs</hi> familie suffred for their Master: And as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:177534:12"/>
                  <hi>Theodoret</hi> saith, when <hi>God</hi> tooke away <hi>Pharaohs</hi> first borne, he open'd a veine in the arme to cure the head, but because it would not be mended, it was destroyed at last it selfe. If then, <hi>Beloved,</hi> we are alwayes bound to mourne and lament, in one sort or another, how much more is it our dutie now, having those three motives together, to be stirred up to <hi>Christian</hi> lamenting, and to shed, 1. <hi>lacry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas doloris,</hi> griefe-teares, for the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable losse we suffer in our owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, by the death of those two Kings, who onely were our comfort, our hope, our shelter, our <hi>Castor</hi> and <hi>Pollux,</hi> according to whom we steered and go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned our ships in the vast Ocean of this troublesome world: of whom it is hard to judge, whether the one suffered and endured, or the other endeavoured and did more, for the advancing and fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of <hi>Gods</hi> glory and religious wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship. But as the <hi>Poet</hi> joyned, <hi>Et agere et pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti fortia,</hi> so we may well pronounce of both, that <hi>the beautie of Israel is slaine: How are the mightie fallen?</hi> Alas! <hi>Beloved,</hi> what
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:177534:12"/> tongue is able to expresse the greatnesse of our losse, and how grievously. <hi>God</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts us by it? A losse which heretofore we never feared, and which now we are not able to describe; that those two <hi>Christian</hi> Kings, should follow one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in lesse then a fort-night, and be snatched from among us by such imma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture death, in the Summer of their age, in the midst of their victories, in the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance to greater hopes, when we were fully perswaded now was the time, they were the men by whom <hi>God</hi> would ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine the Throne of <hi>Antichrist,</hi> and save his <hi>Israel.</hi> But I will rather leave unto you by my silence to consider of this losse, then lessen it for want of requisite expression, This onely I will remember unto you, that, had we as heartily prayed for them whilest they yet lived, as we now hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily lament their death, who knowes but <hi>God</hi> might have prevented our mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting here in the <hi>Vallie</hi> of <hi>Bochim,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stead of that have filled our mouthes with <hi>Alleluiahs.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. As much reason have we to shed
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:177534:13"/>
                  <hi>lacrymas compassionis,</hi> fellow feeling teares: For as we ought to mourne for the trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gression of <hi>Iacob, Mich.</hi> 1. 5. so must we also be grieved for the affliction of <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>seph</hi> If our eyes should be so farre blen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, and our hearts so much hardned, that we could not discerne nor appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend our particular and private miserie, in this common and universall losse of whole <hi>Christendome;</hi> yet let us at least turne our eyes upon the Church of <hi>God,</hi> who lost so great, so faithfull nursing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fathers; upon the Kingdomes of <hi>Sweden</hi> and <hi>Bohemia;</hi> upon our deare <hi>Germanie,</hi> and especially upon our poore <hi>Electorall Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate,</hi> who lost such Kings, such Friends; Let us but turne our eyes upon those pearles of Pietie, the two uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solable Queenes, whose very names we cannot remember without teares and hearts-griefe, upon the Royall, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solate; and yet tender posteritie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of part lost a Father afore they knew him. Can there be any heart so flintie, that would not be moved by the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent teares of those Princely Infants, to
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:177534:13"/> condole with them, when he seeth them weeping for their losse, which, though now they comprehend it not so fully, yet they will too too soone be sensible of it. Though we had no particular share and part in the losse, yet we should have out part in the common griefe of whole <hi>Christendome,</hi> and thus approve our selues living members of <hi>Christs bodie.</hi> It's but a rotten member, a whithered hand, a woodden leg, that is not sensible of the heads wounding. Assuredly such hard hearts, that are void of fellow-fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and compassion towards others in their adversity, are but glasse eyes, silver noses, lvory teeth, and have nothing but the shape and fashion, fill up a roome, but have no use, and yeeld no profit.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Great reason we have to powre out our <hi>lacrymas penitentiae,</hi> repenting teares; which the Apostle 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 10. calleth a <hi>godly sorrow,</hi> which worketh repentance to salvation, never to be repented off Such as <hi>Daniel</hi> shed, <hi>Daniel</hi> 9. And the Church after the death of good <hi>Iosiah,</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially when they sayd in the <hi>Lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:177534:14"/> of <hi>Ieremie; The Crowne is fallen from our head, for this our heart is faint, for these things our eyes are dimme.</hi> Full well may we powre out whole buckets of repenting teares, and by them arraigne our sinnes, as the onely cause and firebrand of our present losse &amp; calamity, saying, <hi>The Crowne is fallen off from our heads, woe unto us that we have sinned;</hi> we have murthered the Kings with our sinnes, we have bereaved the <hi>Queenes</hi> of their dearest consorts; the Royall Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of their Parents, the Countries of their Princes; all this have we done, and for this is our soule perplexed, our eyes are consumed with griefe and waxed old.</p>
               <p>But what then were those cut-throat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sins, that committed this hainous mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther upon the sacred persons of those no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Kings?</p>
               <p>I answer. They were two; Omitting the good, committing the evill; as the Commandements of <hi>God</hi> are two fold, so are the transgressions The <hi>Rabbines,</hi> according to their usuall curiositie, have calculated and summed up all the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:177534:14"/> Commandements of <hi>Moses,</hi> and found 613. wherof 365 are negative and inhibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, shewing us what we ought to shun, in number equalling the dayes of the yeare The rest are affirmative pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts, teaching us what to doe, in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 248. as many as there are bones in a mans bodie; by which division, they would instruct us, that the whole man inward and outward to his very bones, should obserue <hi>Gods</hi> Commandements; and that not for a while onely, but the whole yeare throughout, all the dayes of his life. But to leave those <hi>Rabbines</hi> to their speculations, this is undoubtedly certaine; that there are those two sorts of Commandements in holy Writ, wherein <hi>God</hi> not only teacheth us what to doe, but likewise what to avoide, both which we grossely transgressed, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially in two capitall sinnes: The first whereof, is that most common and yet most heavie sinne of <hi>Vnthankfulnesse; Ingratum si dixeris, omnia dixeris.</hi> The <hi>Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turiators</hi> of <hi>Magdenburgh</hi> in their Preface make a certaine gradation and degrees,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:177534:15"/> in what order <hi>God</hi> brings his punish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments upon us; <hi>Ingentia beneficia, ingentia flagitia, ingentia supplicia.</hi> If <hi>God</hi> shewes ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary mercies &amp; favours to a peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and yet the same continueth multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying its sinnes against <hi>God,</hi> then <hi>God</hi> doth likewise muliply his punishments upon it, till it worke either amendment, or utter destruction Now what people or nation is there, to whom <hi>God</hi> hath imparted so many and so great favours, as to our owne selues? How for a long time hath he blessed us with good Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrates and Governours, what plente<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous peace have we enjoyed, what ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and reputation had we of other Nations? But when we began to slight those benefits, and would not rest con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with them, <hi>God</hi> tooke the rodde into his hand, and gave us severe cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection. Yet, againe did those all-pitty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bowells of our good <hi>God,</hi> yearne towards his poore Church, raising them a Deliverer, a mighty <hi>Iosuah,</hi> in a miraculous manner, all hope being lost, whereby he so much curbed and broke
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:177534:15"/> the Enemie, and so much comforted the disconsolate Church, that it is beyond expression. But how have we in the meane while demeaned our selues to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards our good <hi>God?</hi> Alas! we have provoked him more and more, with our pride, haughtinesse, luxurie, envie, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and all manner of filthinesse, and given him cause to deale with us as it is at this present. Gods servants have good reason to complaine of their people, say<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Deut. 32. 4 God is the rocke, his worke is perfect, for all his wayes are Iudgement; they have corrupted themselues, they are spotted, and are not his children, doe yee thus requite the Lord?</hi> This now is the first sinne, we have not beene thankfull unto <hi>God,</hi> nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in our former peaceable and happy estate for his manifold favours, nor now in our calamitous condition for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer he sent us, therefore hath <hi>God</hi> vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sited us with this sharpe correction.</p>
               <p>The <hi>other sinne</hi> was affirmative, an <hi>over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>great confidence</hi> in impotent man, whom we have Idolized, reposing upon an arme of flesh, bragging and attributing
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:177534:16"/> to mortall Kings, the honour that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to the Eternall, which he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not brooke or connive unto. <hi>Esay 42 8. I will not give mine honour unto another.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hath <hi>God</hi> taken away our Kings to avenge this dishonour, and to vendicate all the honour unto himselfe, to publish throughout the earth, that he was, he is the Lord, that onely worketh won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and that his Throne abideth for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
               <p>If it be so then <hi>Beloved,</hi> that we have so much cause of sorrowing, grieving, weeping, and lamenting, for our selues, for others, and especially for our sinnes; Oh! then let us pray with <hi>Ieremie,</hi> saying, <hi>Ier. 9. 1. O that my head were waters, and mine eyes a fountaine of teares, that I might weepe day and night, for the losse of the daughter of my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and for the sinnes of my youth.</hi> Our <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian</hi> faith allowes no <hi>Stoike</hi> stupiditie and blockish sencelesnesse, called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, by the <hi>Phylosophers,</hi> as that which is averse and repugnant to <hi>Christian</hi> charitie, which is full of tendrest compassion. Though sorrow be bitter at present, and an unsa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorie
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:177534:16"/> portion, and hath such vehement operation, that it enfeebleth all naturall faculties, yet afterwards it worketh <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance never to be repented off</hi> Let the world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings laugh, whilest we are weeping, the turne of weeping will once come to them, when they with grudge shall see us joyfull: let not our hearts be cooled by their coldnesse, but as the bellowes by their cold wind doe blow and kindle the fire, so let their cold affections serue ours as bellowes doe the kindled coales, to enflame them the more, to make them the more zealous &amp; fervent, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifest our <hi>Christian</hi> fellow-feeling before the world, but especially to find out and bewaile our sinnes. Thus <hi>God</hi> shall be honoured, our neighbour comforted, and we restrained and refrained from the wiles and snares of sinne Chiefly let us be frequent and much in conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what we have lost, no trifles, nor such things as we may easily recover else-where; not some children with <hi>Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hel,</hi> or goods with <hi>Lot,</hi> or health with <hi>Iob;</hi> but the <hi>Beautie of Israel, the Mighties of
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:177534:17"/> Iuda,</hi> as we shall heare in the second part of our Text, where <hi>David</hi> saith; <hi>The beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Israel is slaine upon thy high places, how are the Mightie fallen?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <head>THE SECOND PART.</head>
               <p>Our <hi>Royall Prophet</hi> in this part most e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legantly describeth▪ 1. The persons la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented, whom he calleth <hi>The beautie of Is<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, and the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ghties</hi> 2. The manner and fashion of their death, they are <hi>slaine and fallen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For the former, the Originall useth a word signifying <hi>Glorie, beautie, or Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie:</hi> Kings, Princes and Magistrates are the <hi>beautie</hi> and <hi>glory</hi> of a Land, 1. In their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons and qualities, if they are wise and Heroike 2. In their Government, if they undertake and performe such things as may tend to the honour of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries; <hi>Si quod invenerunt regnum lateritium, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linquunt marmoreum.</hi> And <hi>Mighties</hi> those are called, whose experience and courage is seene in difficult warres and encounters, as we have examples in <hi>Ioshua,</hi> in the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:177534:17"/>
                  <hi>Iudges,</hi> and in the mightie men of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For our better understanding of these words, we will briefly survay, what the principallest qualities and imployments of Kings and Princes are, for which they may be called the <hi>Beautie</hi> and <hi>Glorie</hi> of a Land or Nation; Chiefly among the rest these following.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Pietie;</hi> This must be the leader; <hi>A Iove principium:</hi> For <hi>Kings</hi> are called <hi>Gods,</hi> not onely by reason of their Power and Authoritie, but likewise for the holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse and integritie, that is required of <hi>Gods Vice-gerents,</hi> and those that shall carrie his character and Image in their persons here on earth; whence it is, that the first commendation, the word of <hi>God</hi> gives unto good Kings, is, <hi>That they did that, which was right and pleasing in the sight of the Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Iustice; Suum cui{que} tribuere,</hi> to give eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man his due, without respect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons either in punishing evill, or rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding good, for which end <hi>God</hi> hath put <hi>the Sword in their hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="26" facs="tcp:177534:18"/>3. <hi>Bountie</hi> and <hi>goodnesse; mildnesse</hi> and <hi>hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manitie. Quâ proximè ad divinam accedunt natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram:</hi> whereby they doe most neerely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach to the nature of God himselfe: <hi>Parcere subiectis, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Courage</hi> and <hi>Magnanimitie: Cass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>neus</hi> observeth that Kings are annointed, as in many parts of their body, so among others upon their armes, as Organs and Instruments of action; They must be going out and comming in before their people, lead, and protect them. <hi>Numb.</hi> 26. 7.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Wisedome;</hi> The fountaine from which all good actions must be derived, so needfull and profitable, that when <hi>God</hi> offered a whole <hi>Cornucopiae,</hi> a Treasure of all sorts of gifts and graces unto King <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon,</hi> he onely made choice of <hi>Wisedome,</hi> or rather taking it, tooke all, according to <hi>Gods</hi> promise: <hi>Omnia adsunt bona quem pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes est v<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>tus.</hi> Kings are annointed in seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall parts, but onely the head is crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as the Throne and residence of <hi>Wise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi> These now are the ornaments, which if a King or Prince have, He is
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:177534:18"/> the <hi>Beautie, Glorie,</hi> and <hi>Excellencie</hi> of his Land and People.</p>
               <p>Now, <hi>Beloved,</hi> it is needlesse to enlarge my selfe in the application, as that which is notorious to all, that we have a most lively patterne and representation of all those qualities in our two Kings, that now are blessedly resting in the <hi>Lord:</hi> of each of whom we may well say, <hi>Sic ocu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>los, sic ille manus, sic ora ferebat.</hi> For was not his Majestie of <hi>Sweden</hi> of happie memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, one of the lewels of the <hi>Protestant</hi> Princes in those parts, not onely by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son of those rare and celestiall endow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and qualities, that so illustriously shined in his Person; but also for his matchlesse and imparalell Heroike Acts and Expeditions, whereby he ennobled himselfe and his Countries, throughout the Vniverse. So likewise was not his Majestie of <hi>Bohemia</hi> an Orient Pearle, and excellent Gemme, among all the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours and Princes of the Empire, for his ever praise worthy and vertuous disposition, for his constant and unre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prochable endeavour to propagate the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:177534:19"/>
                  <hi>Gospell</hi> of <hi>Christ,</hi> whereby, all unhappie accidents notwithstanding, he hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chased glory and honour both to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selfe and to our common Country.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is universally knowne, without my instancing of it at large, what may be sayd in the commendation of both the Kings constant Tenour of their <hi>Pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie</hi> and <hi>Devotion,</hi> both private and pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like, wherein they have alwayes beene patternes and singular examples to their Subjects and followers; as especially, those are able to witnesse, who had the honour to be much about their Majesties; especially, how carefull and assiduous they have beene in the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>servation of their pray-and reading<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houres, as well in warre, as in peace, as much as possibly they could recover from their infinitely employ'd and bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sied Time, as it is reported and knowne all the world over.</p>
               <p>They write of <hi>Helena,</hi> that, having found the materiall Crosse of <hi>Christ,</hi> and the nayles wherewith hee had beene nailed upon it, shee caused one thereof
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:177534:19"/> to be inserted into the Crowne of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantine</hi> the Emperour, and the other lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked unto his bridle, minding him there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, that <hi>Christ</hi> was not onely his chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest honour, but likewise his bridle and directour. But wee may truely say of our deceased Kings, that <hi>Christ</hi> was their chiefest glory and Diademe; the onely Rule and Compass<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of all their Life and Actions We need no further proofe of their <hi>Pietie,</hi> least we should seeme to make it doubtfull.</p>
               <p>But because Kings especially, are not borne for themselues alone, but for all theirs and for their Subjects, as <hi>Gregorie</hi> the Great speaketh, <hi>Reges in orbe fecit Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus, ut terrestre regnum famuletur caelesti. God</hi> hath given Kingdomes unto Kings, that they should bring their Subjects to the Kingdome of Heaven, and shew them the way unto it. This was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wise a principall care of their Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sties; We have the effect of this godly care of his Majestie of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore our eyes, in the nursing up of the young <hi>Princes</hi> and <hi>Princesses</hi> in all <hi>Pietie</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:177534:20"/> and <hi>Christian</hi> Vertues: and we beare yet in fresh memorie the fatherly care in this kind which he manifested to all his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects in <hi>Bohemia</hi> and in the <hi>Palatinate;</hi> an infallible argument of sincerest pietie: the like his Majestie of <hi>Sweden</hi> ever care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully and praise-worthily intended and furthered to his uttermost. Lastly, if it be an undoubted marke of Christianitie and godlinesse, to fight and suffer for <hi>God</hi> and his Truth, what then shall we say of those two Kings, who partly lost, partly hazarded all their Possessions and Countries, to doe service to <hi>God,</hi> his Church, and the grievously oppressed <hi>Christians,</hi> and to spread and extend the sweete <hi>Gospell</hi> of <hi>Christ?</hi> In a word, we may well and deservedly give them this <hi>Encomium</hi> and commendation out of <hi>Gods</hi> Word, <hi>That they have done what was right and pleasing in Gods eyes. 2 King.</hi> 18. 3.</p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Iustice,</hi> was another Iewell, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with our two Kings were gloriously a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned. How just and impartiall they ever shewed themselues, as well in the publike administration of <hi>Iustice,</hi> as in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:177534:20"/> cases in their owne Courts, is more cleare and manifest then the light of the Sunne, one may as soone disprove one as the other; insomuch, that we may well apply this sentence of <hi>Gods</hi> word unto them, that <hi>The wisedome of God was in them to doe iudgement 1 King.</hi> 3. 28.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Bountie</hi> and <hi>Humanitie;</hi> The third Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well of both their Majesties: the which was seene and praysed in his Majestie of <hi>Bohemia</hi> with admiration, how lovingly and how amiably, yea in a manner fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliarly he carried himselfe to all, even of the lower sort, to his immortall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation. Which as another excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie was likewise observed and highly commended in his Majestie of <hi>Sweden;</hi> how friendly, mildely, and courteously he demeaned himselfe, not onely to those of lower ranke, but towards his very enemies; with whom he could so comport himselfe, <hi>ut Pyrrhus unà fuerit &amp; Cyneas,</hi> that he conquered almost as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and great Cities with his loving be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour, and heart-breaking eloquence, as he did by his valour and courage:
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:177534:21"/> whereof <hi>Elbing</hi> in <hi>Borussia, Frankfurt</hi> upon the <hi>Mayne,</hi> and <hi>Augsburg,</hi> are evident and fresh examples.</p>
               <p>We read indeed in the Histories of many Kings, <hi>qui alienae facundiae egue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>unt, aut illâ vsi sunt,</hi> who either were to be sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed by the eloquence of others out of necessitie, or used it out of pride, And so we read of <hi>Leo,</hi> that he had alwayes <hi>Maiorian</hi> at his elbow, to interpret his minde, <hi>Cuius dignatur ab ore, Caesar in orbe loqui,</hi> as <hi>Sidonius</hi> speakes of him. But <hi>God</hi> had bestowed this singular gift upon the Majesties of these Kings, that they had no need, as <hi>Moses</hi> of an <hi>Aaron,</hi> to be their spokes-man, but <hi>ex tempore,</hi> and without premeditation they were able fully, wisely, and elegantly to expresse their mindes upon any occasion, which often put the hearers into admiration: So that we may say of both, that <hi>They knew to speake from the Cedar that groweth in Lebanon, to the Isop that sprouts out of the wall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. As for <hi>Courage, Valour,</hi> and <hi>undaunted Magnanimitie,</hi> another Iewell againe of the Crownes of those Kings, and which
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:177534:21"/> made them esteemed as the only gemme of the world, consider we their Heroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call resolutions, and that height of cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage they have manifested in so many occasions, Countries, Times, and Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, even <hi>admiraculum us{que}</hi> as the whole world cannot but know, and those doe witnesse, that were <hi>oculati testes,</hi> the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent and constant beholders of it. And we need no other proofe then the many hundred Cities, Forts, Castles, the se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall bloudie battells and victories, the frequent and dangerous skirmishes, and innumerable other warlike expeditions, which were practised onely in <hi>Germanie,</hi> within these two yeares, under the commaund and government of his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jestie of <hi>Sweden.</hi> So that wee may well summe it up all with this part of <hi>Davids</hi> Elegie, 2 <hi>Sam. 1. 22. From the bloud of the slaine, from the fat of the mightie, the bow of Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nathan turned not backe, and the sword of Saul returned not emptie.</hi> And out of <hi>Gen. 49. 9. Iudah is a Lyons whelpe; from the victorie thou art exalted; Hee couched himselfe as a Lyon, as an old Lyon, who durst rouze him up?</hi> But what
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:177534:22"/> doe we endeavour to commend that in his Majestie, which neither present, nor future ages can sufficiently and answera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to desert extoll and magnifie, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though they shall never cease to ring and trumpet his noble fame and memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</p>
               <p n="5">5. There is yet <hi>Wisedome,</hi> that Royall Plant, which seemes was the Master<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piece of all the endowments the heart of those Royall Princes were adorned withall. For, <hi>Beloved,</hi> we may say this with out the least touch of pleasing flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery, that <hi>God</hi> had endowed those two Kings with such understanding and wisedome, that they were admired a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad, and joyfully honoured for it at home, and among their owne: And we could well have applyed to them, what <hi>Plinius</hi> saith of another; <hi>Nihil est omnium quod discere velles, quod illi tedocere non possent:</hi> You could have devised nothing to learne, but you might have learned it of them. Witnesse, the great concourse heretofore to <hi>Heidelberg</hi> from all parts of <hi>Christendome,</hi> as to the <hi>Delphik Oracle,</hi> and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:177534:22"/> afterwards to his Maiestie of <hi>Sweden,</hi> for counsell, helpe, redresse, and reliefe. In a word for the brevitie of Time, we may without blasphemie, pronounce of their Maiesties <hi>that the Heavenly wisedome had built her a house in the hearts of those Kings, Pro.</hi> 9. 1. which will preserue the Remembrance of their Names to perpetuity.</p>
               <p>And now I had almost made this ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall conclusion of both Kings, with that of the Scripture, 2. <hi>Chron.</hi> 1. 12. that, <hi>scarce was any the like before them, and hardly will such come after them</hi> as were themselues: but that the Phylosopher puts mee in minde of his, <hi>Ante obilum nemo, suprema{que} <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ata beatus:</hi> And therefore it is requisite that according to the subdivision of our Text, we consider with <hi>David</hi> the <hi>manner and fashion</hi> of the death of our deceased, and with all how happie our <hi>Kings</hi> were in the same. I shall not be long in this matter, it toucheth too neere to the quicke: would to <hi>God</hi> we had never had occasion to heare or speake of these, to us, most dolefull deaths But as with all good <hi>Kings,</hi> so went it with these, <hi>Venit
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:177534:23"/> summa dies &amp; inevitabile fatum The beauty of Isra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el is slaine upon thy high places! How are the mighty fallen?</hi> I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> is remarkeable how that <hi>royal Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet</hi> describeth their death; though they <hi>were slaine,</hi> yet doth he add they <hi>were but fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len; Cadunt, non occidunt, abeunt, non obeunt, prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eunt, non pereunt,</hi> which though it could not be applyed to <hi>Saul,</hi> yet of <hi>Ionathan</hi> it was certaine; <hi>They are fallen!</hi> So these, but they will rise againe, they are gone, but not pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rished, they are gone before, but not lost: they will not come to us againe, well we may goe to them. <hi>Beloved,</hi> it would breake not onely the tenderest, but the hardest heart, to consider how resolvedly, and quietly both Kings have left this mise<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Wildernesse, and how, as <hi>Ambrose</hi> speaketh, <hi>regnum non deseruerunt, sed mutârunt:</hi> They have not put off their Crownes, but onely changed them. His Majestie of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> did so holily and comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly resolue and fit himselfe divers dayes before with reading, praying, &amp; singing e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>specially the last night against the approa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching death; in the presence of divers of his Courtiers &amp; Ministers, till death came
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:177534:23"/> which seemed rather to be a sleepe, his life failing and spending as the light of a dying candle. How resolutely and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragiously likewise his Majestie of <hi>Sweden</hi> hath encoūtred his death, none is able to expresse sufficiently, as we easily may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, if we waigh but a little one of his last discourses, praying that none would giudge him the honor <hi>God</hi> would bestow upō him, that he should loose his life for <hi>Gods word,</hi> &amp; shed his blood for the <hi>German Liberty:</hi> exhorting withall the Princes and Commanders, to go on couragiously w<seg rend="sup">th</seg> the Worke they had begunne, that none should looke upon him, an Instrument &amp; Minister, but upon <hi>God</hi> the <hi>Mover</hi> &amp; <hi>Master</hi> who doubtlesly would blesse their ende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, if their aime be &amp; continue sincere, &amp; that they onely would seeke the mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifying of his glory; that hitherto he had done what he could, hoping none could lay any evill to his charg, that could have beene prevented by him. And thus both Kings blessedly departed in the <hi>Lord</hi> &amp; as the <hi>Scripture phrase</hi> is, <hi>obd<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rmierunt,</hi> they fell a-sleepe, leaving behind them as <hi>Pliniu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="38" facs="tcp:177534:24"/> words are, <hi>duas Reginas &amp; mille virtutes,</hi> Two disconsolate Queenes, and a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sand Heroicall vertues. Therefore wee conclude in the words of <hi>David 2. Sam. 1. 23. They were lovely and pleasant in their lives, and in their death they were not divided, they were swifter then Eagles, they were stronger then Ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lastly, it is worth observation, that as <hi>Samson</hi> slue more <hi>Philistines</hi> in his death, then all his life time; so the two Kings have obtained nobler victories in their Death, then even before; and thus en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred the new <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> as it were in a Chariot of Tryumph, as it is apparant, out of that strange and miraculous vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory the dead <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Sweden</hi> obtained, and out of the rendring up of the Citie and Fort of <hi>Franken<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>all,</hi> into the hands of the dead <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Bohemia.</hi> Thus have we viewed a patterne and lively <hi>contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fact,</hi> of a pious and Heroike Prince, in the example of those two excellent Kings; to passe by many other and most commendable vertues, wherewith as <hi>Christians,</hi> they were endowed and ador<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:177534:24"/> But now some malicious scoffers may rise up and say, what, had those Kings nothing but perfections, that all this while we have nothing rehearsed but their praises and vertues. I answer; Alas! <hi>Beloved, Homines fuerunt.</hi> They were men, as we are; they had their infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, as we have; who lives and sinnes not? But as <hi>Apelles,</hi> when he drew the picture of <hi>Antigonus</hi> painted onely the one side of his face, thus to hide and cover his infirmitie, he wanting an eye upon the other hidden side: So must we doe with our Princes; remember and propound unto the view of the World, whatsoever of theirs was praise-worthy and commendable, to adde spurres and incouragements unto us to follow and imitate their example in all <hi>Christian</hi> ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues. As for the faults and infirmities, the Apostle tells us, that <hi>Love doth cover a multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of sinnes, Iam.</hi> 5. 20. Especially, where the multitude and excellencie of vertues doe cover and excell the imperfections, the which we can and doe truely averre of our deceased Kings. What remaineth
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:177534:25"/> then, but that with the <hi>Centurion</hi> having seene their death, wee comprehend all their commendations in one word: <hi>Of a truth those have beene the sonnes and children of God. Mat.</hi> 27, 54,</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>OF THE THIRD PART.</head>
               <p>Now for conclusion, How ought we to behave and demeane our selues after this fall and losse of ours? The Time be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alreadie past, and the season cold, I will onely intimate some few rules, how we shall profit our selues upon this mournefull accident, and so con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>Telt it not at Gath, Publish it not in the streetes: of Askelon, &amp;c.</hi> Why? I trow the <hi>Israelites</hi> would send no Messengers to <hi>Gath,</hi> to bring the newes to the <hi>Philistines,</hi> that they had lost <hi>Saul</hi> their King. O no, <hi>Beloved,</hi> but we tell bad nevves at <hi>Gath,</hi> by our excessive complaining and cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, if we cast off all comfort, and doe as if we would despaire. Then we tell our Enemies as it were, that all our hope
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:177534:25"/> is gone, that we are quite undone, we give them occasion to tickle and sport themselues, to grow proud and insolent upon our losses; And therfore we ought to moderate our lamenting and mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and to shew by it unto the world that <hi>God</hi> is still continuing in heaven, on whom we depend. The <hi>Kings</hi> are dead indeed, but <hi>God</hi> lives for ever; his hand is not shorter, his arme is not weaker. At least, let us shew our confidence in the eyes and presence of the wicked and scoffers, and though our heart lies blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as it cannot but bleed for a long time yet, the wound being so fierce and deepe; yet let us so order our comport<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and conversation, that we mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fest our dependance and confidence in <hi>God,</hi> and make no sport and pastime to the wicked by our immoderate grieving and lamenting.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Withall let us looke once somewhat more seriously upon the <hi>Nature of sinne,</hi> what infinitenesse and greatnesse of evils it hath brought upon all the children of <hi>Adam.</hi> Sorrow and griefe is one of those
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:177534:26"/> herbes and simples the earth yeeldeth not, afore it was dunged with sinne. It is a weed, that sprouted immediately out of that bitter roote of our first <hi>Apostacie.</hi> And as it came into the world with sin, so it will ever remaine with it, till sinne and world be both destroyed and pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish. As much therefore as we desire to prevent those naturall griefes and sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowes, so let us take heed of sinne; Let us often thinke of sinne, and that which followes sinne at the heeles, and then we will shunne sinne, to shunne the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>evitable after-claps of sorrowfull misery and grievous punishments. Thus, as thornes and thistles are good to hedge in a pleasant garden, to keepe out wild and wasting creatures, so will sinne like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wife be good, to be rooted in our me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morie, to remember both it, and the grievous consequents of it, but not good to plant any in our hearts, to feed and harbour it there, to spoile and cumber the ground. Let us therefore now seri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ously repent us of our sinnes, acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, confesse, bewaile, denie, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:177534:26"/> forsake, avoid, and hate them, and be assured <hi>God</hi> will make up the breach hee made in <hi>Israel,</hi> perfect the building of the Walls of <hi>Ierusalem,</hi> and wipe off those teares from our eyes, and turne them into joy and gladnesse.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Let us learne to put all our <hi>Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in God alone,</hi> and build all our com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort upon that sure rocke: Ah! how often doth he repeate and inculcate this lesson unto us in his blessed word. <hi>Psal. 146. 3. 4. 5. Put not your confidence in Princes, they are men and cannot helpe, their breath goeth forth, they returne to earth, in that very day their thoughts perish.</hi> Yea he hath confirmed this truth unto us by our woefull and dole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full experience, and convinced us of it to our cost and griefe; <hi>But hoppie is he, that hath the God of Iacob for his helpe, whose hope is in the Lord his God; The Lord doth raigne for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, even thy God O Sion to all generations.</hi> This should alwayes bee our comfort to up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold us, especially in our present mournefull condition; <hi>God</hi> hath taken away our Kings and gracious Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raignes, yet He is not taken away but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bideth
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:177534:27"/> for ever. Hee will supply their places, He will be the Governour of the desolate Countries, a gracious King to the destitute Subjects, a Generall to the faithfull Souldiers, a Husband to the Royall Widdowes, a Father to the Roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Progenie, yea all in all to all. He will raise up other <hi>Ioshua's</hi> and <hi>Iosia's,</hi> that shall finish his worke, if we will but learne and practice this good lesson, to trust &amp; relie wholy and onelly upon him. Saint <hi>Ambrose</hi> comforted the people after the death of <hi>Theodosius</hi> in this manner; <hi>Disce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, sed non totus; reliquit enim liberos, in quibus ipsum cernamis;</hi> He is gone, but not whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for he left children, in whom we may see him still. Yea, but say they, the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren are young? No saith he, they are not young: <hi>aetas est perfecta, ubi virtus est perfecta:</hi> the age is perfect, when vertue is perfect. To the Kingdome of <hi>Sweden, God</hi> hath left a Queen, of the seed of that glorious King of theirs; And so hath the <hi>Electorall Palatinate</hi> a true Heire and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessour, who shall goe in and out before his people; in whom, <hi>God</hi> continuing
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:177534:27"/> his grace and favour, wee shall find a change of the person, but not of the roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all vertues and endowments; <hi>Tu Marcel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus eris:</hi> what great cause have we yet further to depend upon <hi>God,</hi> who alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy doth give us such hopes of happie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-times.</p>
               <p n="4">4. For our Conclusion, let us discerne the <hi>vanitie of all outward things,</hi> and the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pines of them that died in the <hi>Lord;</hi> Let us not grudge them their blessed estate, but endeavour, how we may follow them. The <hi>Scripture</hi> hath very elegant expressi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the death of the godly, that <hi>God gives them rest from their sorrowes, and from their feares, and from their hard bondage, wherin they were made to serue, Esay</hi> 14. 3. There is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in this world but labour and paine sorrow and hearts griefe, as we have seene it in the example of our deceased blessed Kings, whose whole life was circumscribed with <hi>Dolor &amp; Labor,</hi> paine and travell, miserie and calamitie. If we take any thing in hand to doe, we grow wearie; if we sit idle, the very idlenesse is tedious and irkesome unto us: who then
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:177534:28"/> would be in love with this life, whose Prologue is <hi>weeping,</hi> whose Act is <hi>weeping,</hi> whose Epilogue is <hi>weeping.</hi> Here cryeth one, <hi>My head, my head,</hi> with the <hi>Widdowes</hi> sonne of <hi>Sunem;</hi> There moanes another, <hi>My belly, my belly,</hi> with the Children of the <hi>Prophets;</hi> Yonder is a third lamenting, <hi>My Sonne, my Sonne,</hi> with <hi>David;</hi> There stands a fourth calling, <hi>My Father, my Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> with <hi>Elisha.</hi> One bewailes his <hi>chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren</hi> with <hi>Rachell,</hi> another faints for <hi>hunger</hi> with <hi>Esau,</hi> a third mournes for his <hi>sinnes</hi> with <hi>David,</hi> a fourth groanes under his <hi>sicknesse</hi> with <hi>Hezekiah.</hi> Nothing but cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, weeping, mourning and lamenting: And yet how loth we are to leave this wretched World: The reason is, we have not yet sufficiently tasted the bitternesse of it; and therefore, that we may not love, but loath it, <hi>God</hi> must fill us another cup. What strange conditioned people are we, that we have beene willing and ready to follow both these Kings to any Country, battell, danger, hazard, yea whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther not, as long as they were here on earth; and now none cares nor thinkes
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:177534:28"/> how to follow them into Heaven, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petually to live and triumph with them. Let us then live as they lived, if we will die, as they dyed; yea, if we will live, as now they live. No question, if we doe follow their example, <hi>Christ</hi> will alwaies be our Life, and Death our Gaine: and after our Worke done here on earth, we shall sit downe to Supper with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham, Isaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob,</hi> and with the blessed Quire of Angells, sing perpetuall <hi>Hallelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iahs</hi> to the <hi>Lord,</hi> and partake of that joy, which is at the right hand of <hi>God</hi> forever and ever. <hi>Whereunto God graunt and helpe us to be advanced, for our blessed Redeemers sake, to whom, together with the holy Ghost, be glorie and thankes for evermore.</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:177534:29"/>
            <head>APOTHEOSIS GVSTAVI MAGNI, Suecorum, Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorum, Vandalorum, &amp;c. Regis.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>Hic, ille Vindex Magnus Orbis, Hercules</l>
               <l>Non falsus, &amp; non editus falso Iove;</l>
               <l>Sed a potentiore missus Numine,</l>
               <l>Monstris domandis, &amp; tuendis gentibus</l>
               <l>Adversus impias Tyrannorum minas.</l>
               <l>Hic, quicquid Illum somniavit Graecia</l>
               <l>Fecisse, fecit; vera{que} ultra fabulam est</l>
               <l>Enixa virtus. Ergo pro Laboribus</l>
               <l>Heros receptus contubernio <hi>Deûm,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Caeli refulget non inanis Gloria.</l>
            </lg>
            <byline>I. FORESTVS.</byline>
            <pb facs="tcp:177534:29"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>